Erez Lieberman Aiden: Everyone knows
إيريز ليبرمان ايدن: الجميع يعرف
that a picture is worth a thousand words.
أن الصورة تعادل الف كلمة.
But we at Harvard
لكننا في هارفارد
were wondering if this was really true.
تساءلنا ما إذا كان ذلك بالفعل صحيحا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So we assembled a team of experts,
وبالتالي جمعنا فريقا من الخبراء،
spanning Harvard, MIT,
يمتدون في هارفارد وMIT
The American Heritage Dictionary, The Encyclopedia Britannica
قاموس التراث الأمريكي، موسوعة بريتانيكا
and even our proud sponsors,
وحتى رعاتنا الذين نفتخر بهم،
the Google.
غوغل.
And we cogitated about this
ودبرنا هذا
for about four years.
لحوالي أربع سنوات.
And we came to a startling conclusion.
ووصلنا إلى استنتاج مبدئي،
Ladies and gentlemen, a picture is not worth a thousand words.
سيداتي سادتي، الصورة لا تعادل الف كلمة.
In fact, we found some pictures
في الحقيقة، وجدنا بعض الصور
that are worth 500 billion words.
التي تقدر بأكثر من 500 مليار كلمة.
Jean-Baptiste Michel: So how did we get to this conclusion?
جان باتيست ميشال: إذن كيف وصلنا إلى هذا الاستنتاج؟
So Erez and I were thinking about ways
إذن أنا وإريز كنا نفكر في طرق
to get a big picture of human culture
للحصول على صورة كبيرة للثقافة الإنسانية
and human history: change over time.
والتاريخ البشري: تغيرها عبر الزمن.
So many books actually have been written over the years.
وهكذا الكثير من الكتب تم تأليفها على مدى السنوات.
So we were thinking, well the best way to learn from them
وبالتالي كنا نفكر، حسنا أفضل طريقة للاستفادة منها
is to read all of these millions of books.
هو قراءة كل هذه الملايين من الكتب.
Now of course, if there's a scale for how awesome that is,
الآن بالطبع، إن كان هناك مقياس لمدى روعة ذلك،
that has to rank extremely, extremely high.
كان هذا ليصنف عاليا وعاليا للغاية.
Now the problem is there's an X-axis for that,
الآن المشكل هو أن هناك محور أفاصيل لذلك،
which is the practical axis.
والذي هو محور العملية.
This is very, very low.
هذا متدن متدن للغاية.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Now people tend to use an alternative approach,
الآن الناس يميلون إلى استخدام مقاربة بديلة،
which is to take a few sources and read them very carefully.
والتي هي أخذ بضعة مصادر وقرائتها بعناية.
This is extremely practical, but not so awesome.
هذا عملي للغاية، لكن ليس بتلك الروعة.
What you really want to do
ما تريد فعله حقا
is to get to the awesome yet practical part of this space.
هو أخذ الجزء الرائع والعملي كذلك من هذا الفضاء.
So it turns out there was a company across the river called Google
وقد اتضح أن هناك شركة على الجانب الآخر من النهر تدعى غوغل
who had started a digitization project a few years back
والتي بدأت مشروع رقمنة قبل بضع سنوات
that might just enable this approach.
من شأنه أن يسمح بهذه المقاربة.
They have digitized millions of books.
قاموا برقمنة ملايين الكتب.
So what that means is, one could use computational methods
وبالتالي ما يعنيه ذلك هو، قد يستخدم المرء طرقا حوسبية
to read all of the books in a click of a button.
لقراءة كل الكتب بضغطة زر.
That's very practical and extremely awesome.
هذا في غاية العملية والروعة.
ELA: Let me tell you a little bit about where books come from.
إ. ل. أ: دعوني أخبركم قليلا من أين تأتي الكتب.
Since time immemorial, there have been authors.
منذ قديم الزمن، تواجد كتّاب.
These authors have been striving to write books.
هؤلاء الكتّاب كانوا يسعون لتأليف كتب.
And this became considerably easier
وقد صار ذلك سهلا جدا
with the development of the printing press some centuries ago.
مع تطور الصحافة المطبوعة قبل بضعة قرون.
Since then, the authors have won
منذ ذلك الوقت، استطاع الكتاب
on 129 million distinct occasions,
على مدى 129 مليون مناسبة متميزة،
publishing books.
من نشر الكتب.
Now if those books are not lost to history,
الآن إن لم تكن تلك الكتب مفقودة في التاريخ،
then they are somewhere in a library,
فإنها في مكان ما في مكتبة،
and many of those books have been getting retrieved from the libraries
والكثير من تلك الكتب يتم استرجاعها من المكتبات
and digitized by Google,
ورقمنتها من قبل غوغل،
which has scanned 15 million books to date.
والذين قاموا بمسح 15 مليون كتاب لحد الساعة.
Now when Google digitizes a book, they put it into a really nice format.
الآن حين يقوم غوغل برقمنة كتاب، يضعونه في شكل أنيق للغاية.
Now we've got the data, plus we have metadata.
الآن لدينا البيانات بالإضافة إلى البيانات الوصفية.
We have information about things like where was it published,
لدينا معلومات حول أمور مثل أين تم نشره،
who was the author, when was it published.
من كان المؤلف، متى تم نشره.
And what we do is go through all of those records
وما نقوم به هو القراء من خلال كل هذه السجلات
and exclude everything that's not the highest quality data.
وإلغاء كل البيانات التي ليست ذات جودة عالية.
What we're left with
ما يتبقى لنا
is a collection of five million books,
هو مجموعة من خمسة ملايين كتاب،
500 billion words,
500 مليار كلمة،
a string of characters a thousand times longer
سلسلة من الأحرف أطول بألف مرة
than the human genome --
من الجينوم البشري --
a text which, when written out,
نص إن تمت كتابته،
would stretch from here to the Moon and back
سيمتد من هنا إلى القمر وعودة
10 times over --
10 مرات متوالية --
a veritable shard of our cultural genome.
قشرة حقيقية لجينومنا الثقافي.
Of course what we did
ما قمنا به بالطبع
when faced with such outrageous hyperbole ...
حين واجهنا تلك المبالغة الفظيعة ..
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
was what any self-respecting researchers
هو ماكان أي باحث يحترم نفسه
would have done.
ليقوم به.
We took a page out of XKCD,
أخذنا صفحة من إكس كي سي دي،
and we said, "Stand back.
وقلنا، "ارجع للوراء.
We're going to try science."
سنجرب العلم."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
JM: Now of course, we were thinking,
ج. م: الآن بالطبع، كنا نفكر،
well let's just first put the data out there
حسنا، دعونا أولا نضع البيانات فقط هناك
for people to do science to it.
حتى يمارس عليها الناس العلم.
Now we're thinking, what data can we release?
الآن كنا نفكر، ما نوع البيانات التي قد نصدرها؟
Well of course, you want to take the books
حسنا بالطبع، تريد أخذ كل الكتب
and release the full text of these five million books.
ونشر النص الكامل لتلك الخمس ملايين كتاب.
Now Google, and Jon Orwant in particular,
الآن غوغل، وجون أوروانت تحديدا،
told us a little equation that we should learn.
أخبرونا عن معادلة صغيرة علينا تعلمها.
So you have five million, that is, five million authors
حسنا لديكم خمس ملايين، هذا يعني، خمس ملايين كاتب
and five million plaintiffs is a massive lawsuit.
وخمس ملايين مدعي هي دعوى قضائية هائلة.
So, although that would be really, really awesome,
إذن، على الرغم من أن هذا كان ليكون رائعا للغاية،
again, that's extremely, extremely impractical.
مجددا، إنه غير عملي للغاية.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now again, we kind of caved in,
الآن مجددا، أذعنا نوعا ما،
and we did the very practical approach, which was a bit less awesome.
وأنجزنا المقاربة العملية جدا، والتي لم تكن بتلك الروعة.
We said, well instead of releasing the full text,
قلنا، حسنا بدل نشر النصوص الكاملة،
we're going to release statistics about the books.
سنقوم بنشر إحصائيات حول الكتب.
So take for instance "A gleam of happiness."
إذن على سبيل المثال "بصيص من السعادة."
It's four words; we call that a four-gram.
إنها أربع كلمات؛ نسمي ذلك أربعة-غرام
We're going to tell you how many times a particular four-gram
سنقوم باخباركم بعدد المرات التي ظهرت فيها أربعة-غرام معينة
appeared in books in 1801, 1802, 1803,
في الكتب في 1801، 1802، 1803،
all the way up to 2008.
على طول الطريق إلى 2008.
That gives us a time series
ذلك يعطينا تسلسلا زمنيا
of how frequently this particular sentence was used over time.
حول مدى تردد استخدام هذه الجملة المعينة مع مرور الزمن.
We do that for all the words and phrases that appear in those books,
نقوم بذلك لكل الكلمات والجمل التي تظهر في تلك الكتب،
and that gives us a big table of two billion lines
وذلك يعطينا جدولا ضخما من ملياري سطر
that tell us about the way culture has been changing.
يخبرنا حول الطريقة التي تتغير بها الثقافة.
ELA: So those two billion lines,
إ. ل. أ: وبالتالي هذان الملياران،
we call them two billion n-grams.
نسميهما ملياري ن-غرام.
What do they tell us?
ما الذي تخبرنا؟
Well the individual n-grams measure cultural trends.
حسنا ال: ن-غرام المفردة تقيس الاتجاهات الثقافية.
Let me give you an example.
دعوني أعطيكم مثالا.
Let's suppose that I am thriving,
دعونا نفترض أنني في ازدهار،
then tomorrow I want to tell you about how well I did.
ثم أردت إخباركم في الغد كيف أبليت حسنا.
And so I might say, "Yesterday, I throve."
وبالتالي قد أقول، "البارحة قد نجحت."
Alternatively, I could say, "Yesterday, I thrived."
كبديل، يمكنني القول، "البارحة، ازدهرت."
Well which one should I use?
حسنا أي واحدة يمكنني استخدامها؟
How to know?
كيف أعرف؟
As of about six months ago,
قبل ستة أشهر من الآن،
the state of the art in this field
أعلى تقدم تقني في المجال
is that you would, for instance,
كان أن تقوم، على سبيل المثال،
go up to the following psychologist with fabulous hair,
بالذهاب إلى عالم نفساني بشعر رائع،
and you'd say,
وتقول،
"Steve, you're an expert on the irregular verbs.
"ستيف، أنت خبير في الأفعال غير النظامية.
What should I do?"
ما الذي يجدر بي فعله؟"
And he'd tell you, "Well most people say thrived,
وسيقول لك، "حسنا معظم الناس يقولون نجحت،
but some people say throve."
لكن بعضهم يقول ازدهرت."
And you also knew, more or less,
وتعلم كذلك، أكثر أو أقل،
that if you were to go back in time 200 years
أنه إن عدت 200 سنة إلى الوراء
and ask the following statesman with equally fabulous hair,
وسألت رجل دولة بنفس الشعر الرائع،
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
"Tom, what should I say?"
"توم، ما الذي يجدر بي قوله؟"
He'd say, "Well, in my day, most people throve,
سيقول، "حسنا، في وقتنا، معظم الناس يزدهرون،
but some thrived."
لكن بعضعهم ينجحون."
So now what I'm just going to show you is raw data.
وبالتالي الآن ما سأعرضهم عليهم هو بينات خام.
Two rows from this table of two billion entries.
صفان من هذا جدول ملياري مدخلة.
What you're seeing is year by year frequency
ما ترونه هو تردد سنة بسنة
of "thrived" and "throve" over time.
لـ "نجح" و"ازدهر" على مرور الزمن.
Now this is just two
الآن هذه فقط اثنتان
out of two billion rows.
من ملياري صف.
So the entire data set
وبالتالي مجموع البيانات الكلية
is a billion times more awesome than this slide.
هي مليار مرة أكثر روعة من هذه الشريحة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
JM: Now there are many other pictures that are worth 500 billion words.
ج. م: الآن هناك الكثير من الصور الأخرى التي تعادل 500 مليار كلمة.
For instance, this one.
على سبيل المثال، هذه.
If you just take influenza,
إن أخذتم الإنفلونزا
you will see peaks at the time where you knew
سترون ذرى في الأوقات التي تعرفون
big flu epidemics were killing people around the globe.
كانت تقتل فيه أوبئة الأنفلونزا الكبرى الناس في جميع أنحاء العالم.
ELA: If you were not yet convinced,
إ. ل. أ: إن لم تكونوا بعد مقتنعين،
sea levels are rising,
مستويات البحر ترتفع،
so is atmospheric CO2 and global temperature.
وكذلك ثنائي أكسيد الكربون في الجو والحرارة العالمية.
JM: You might also want to have a look at this particular n-gram,
ج. م: سترغبون كذلك في إلقاء نظرة على هذا الـ ن-غرام بذاته،
and that's to tell Nietzsche that God is not dead,
وذلك لإخبار نيتشه أن الإله ليس ميتا،
although you might agree that he might need a better publicist.
على الرغم من أنه قد يحتاج وكيلا إعلاميا أفضل.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
ELA: You can get at some pretty abstract concepts with this sort of thing.
إ. ل. أ: يمكنكم الحصول على بعض المفاهيم المجردة بهذا الشيء.
For instance, let me tell you the history
على سبيل المثال، دعوني أخبركم عن تاريخ
of the year 1950.
السنة 1950.
Pretty much for the vast majority of history,
للغالبية العظمى من التاريخ،
no one gave a damn about 1950.
لم يهتم أحد في حدود 1950.
In 1700, in 1800, in 1900,
في 1700 في 1800 في 1900،
no one cared.
لم يهتم أحد.
Through the 30s and 40s,
خلال الثلاثينيات والأربعينيات،
Suddenly, in the mid-40s,
وفجأة، في منتصف الأربعينيات،
there started to be a buzz.
بدأت تحدث ضجة.
People realized that 1950 was going to happen,
بدأ الناس يدركون أن 1950 قادمة،
and it could be big.
وقد تكون عظيمة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But nothing got people interested in 1950
لكن لا شيء جعل الناس أكثر اهتماما بـ 1950
like the year 1950.
مثل السنة 1950.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
People were walking around obsessed.
كان الناس يمشون مهووسين.
They couldn't stop talking
لم يستطيعوا التوقف عن الكلام
about all the things they did in 1950,
حول ما قاموا به في 1950،
all the things they were planning to do in 1950,
كل ما كانوا يخططون له في 1950،
all the dreams of what they wanted to accomplish in 1950.
كل الأحلام حول ما أرادوا إنجازه في 1950.
In fact, 1950 was so fascinating
في الواقع، 1950 كان آسرا لدرجة
that for years thereafter,
أنه في السنوات اللاحقة،
people just kept talking about all the amazing things that happened,
بقي الناس يتحدثون حول كل الأمور الرائعة التي حدثت،
in '51, '52, '53.
في 51 و 52 و53.
Finally in 1954,
وأخير في 1954،
someone woke up and realized
أحدهم استيقظ وأدرك
that 1950 had gotten somewhat passé.
أن 1950 قد انقضت.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And just like that, the bubble burst.
وبكل بساطة، انفجرت الفقاعة.
And the story of 1950
وقصة 1950
is the story of every year that we have on record,
هي قصة كل سنة لدينا في السجلات،
with a little twist, because now we've got these nice charts.
بالتفاف بسيط، لأنه لدينا الآن هذه المبيانات الجميلة.
And because we have these nice charts, we can measure things.
ولأنه لدينا مبيانات جميلة، يمكننا قياس الأشياء.
We can say, "Well how fast does the bubble burst?"
يمكننا القول، "حسنا ما مدى سرعة انفجار الفقاعة؟"
And it turns out that we can measure that very precisely.
وقد اتضح أنه يمكننا قياس ذلك بدقة بالغة.
Equations were derived, graphs were produced,
تم اشتقاق معادلات، وإنتاج رسوم بيانية،
and the net result
والنتيجة الخام
is that we find that the bubble bursts faster and faster
هي أنه وجدنا أن الفقاعة تنفجر بسرعة أكثر فأكثر
with each passing year.
مع مرور كل سنة.
We are losing interest in the past more rapidly.
نحن نفقد اهتمامنا بالماضي بشكل أكثر سرعة.
JM: Now a little piece of career advice.
ج. م: الآن نصيحة مهنية بسيطة.
So for those of you who seek to be famous,
وبالتالي لمن يريد منكم أن يشتهر،
we can learn from the 25 most famous political figures,
يمكننا الاستفادة من الشخصيات السياسية الـ 25 الأكثر شهرة،
authors, actors and so on.
والكتاب والممثلين وما إلى ذلك.
So if you want to become famous early on, you should be an actor,
وبالتالي إذا ما أردت أن تصبح مشهورا لاحقا، يجدر بك أن تصير ممثلا،
because then fame starts rising by the end of your 20s --
لأن الشهرة تبدأ بالزيادة في نهاية العشرينيات --
you're still young, it's really great.
لا تزال يافعا، ذلك عظيم للغاية.
Now if you can wait a little bit, you should be an author,
الآن إن أمكنك الانتظار قليلا، يجدر بك أن تصير كاتبا،
because then you rise to very great heights,
لأنه آنذاك ترتفع إلى مستويات عظيمة،
like Mark Twain, for instance: extremely famous.
مثل مارك توين، على سبيل المثال: في غاية الشهرة.
But if you want to reach the very top,
لكن إن أردت أن تصل إلى أعلى القمة،
you should delay gratification
يجدر بك أن تؤجل المتعة،
and, of course, become a politician.
وتصير سياسيا بالطبع.
So here you will become famous by the end of your 50s,
وبالتالي هنا ستصير مشهورا في نهاية خمسينياتك،
and become very, very famous afterward.
وستصير مشهورا للغاية بعد ذلك.
So scientists also tend to get famous when they're much older.
والعلماء كذلك يميلون إلى أن يصيروا مشهورين حين يكونون أكبر بكثير.
Like for instance, biologists and physics
على سبيل المثال، الأحيائيون والفيزيائيون
tend to be almost as famous as actors.
يصيرون بقدر شهرة الممثلين.
One mistake you should not do is become a mathematician.
خطأ واحد لا يجدر بكم الوقوع فيه هو أن تصيروا رياضياتيين.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
If you do that,
إن قمتم بذلك،
you might think, "Oh great. I'm going to do my best work when I'm in my 20s."
قد تعتقدون، "أوه عظيم. سأقوم بأعظم أعمالي في العشرينيات من عمري"
But guess what, nobody will really care.
لكن خمنوا ماذا، لا أحد في الواقع يهتم.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
ELA: There are more sobering notes
إ. ل. أ: هناك ملاحظات حكيمة أخرى
among the n-grams.
فيما بين الـ ن-غرام.
For instance, here's the trajectory of Marc Chagall,
على سبيل المثال، هنا تجدون مسار مارك شاغال،
an artist born in 1887.
فنان ولد سنة 1887.
And this looks like the normal trajectory of a famous person.
ويبدو هذا مثل مسار شخص مشهور عادي.
He gets more and more and more famous,
يصير أكثر وأكثر شهرة،
except if you look in German.
باستثناء إن بحثتم بالألمانية.
If you look in German, you see something completely bizarre,
إن بحثتم بالألمانية، ترون شيئا غريبا للغاية،
something you pretty much never see,
شيئا لا ترونه أبدا،
which is he becomes extremely famous
وهو أن تصير مشهورا للغاية
and then all of a sudden plummets,
ثم وفجأة،
going through a nadir between 1933 and 1945,
يصل الحضيض ما بين 1933 و1945،
before rebounding afterward.
قبل أن يرتد مجددا لاحقا.
And of course, what we're seeing
وبالطبع، ما ترونه
is the fact Marc Chagall was a Jewish artist
هو حقيقة كون مارك شاغال فنانا يهوديا
in Nazi Germany.
في ألمانيا النازية.
Now these signals
الآن هذه الإشارات
are actually so strong
هي في الواقع قوية للغاية
that we don't need to know that someone was censored.
لدرجة أنه لا تحتاج إلى معرفة أن أحدهم كان تحت الرقابة.
We can actually figure it out
يمكننا في الواقع إستنتاج ذلك
using really basic signal processing.
باستخدام معالجة إشارات أساسية.
Here's a simple way to do it.
هنا طريقة بسيطة للقيام بذلك.
Well, a reasonable expectation
حسنا، توقع منطقي
is that somebody's fame in a given period of time
هو أن شهرة أحدهم في فترة زمنية معينة
should be roughly the average of their fame before
يجب أن تكون تقريبا معدل شهرتهم قبل
and their fame after.
وبعد الاشتهار.
So that's sort of what we expect.
وبالتالي ذلك نوع مما نتوقعه.
And we compare that to the fame that we observe.
ونقارن ذلك بالشهرة التي نلاحظها.
And we just divide one by the other
ونقسم واحدا بالآخر
to produce something we call a suppression index.
لإنتاج شيء نسميه مؤشر القمع.
If the suppression index is very, very, very small,
إن كان مؤشر القمع صغيرا جدا للغاية،
then you very well might be being suppressed.
بعد ذلك قد تكون أنت ذاتك تحت القمع.
If it's very large, maybe you're benefiting from propaganda.
إن كان كبيرا للغاية، ربما تكون مستفيدا من بروباغاندا.
JM: Now you can actually look at
ج. م: الآن يمكنكم فعلا أن تنظروا
the distribution of suppression indexes over whole populations.
توزيع مؤشرات القمع على لمجموع السكان.
So for instance, here --
لذا على سبيل المثال، هنا --
this suppression index is for 5,000 people
مؤشر القمع هذا هو لـ 5000 شخص
picked in English books where there's no known suppression --
تم اختيارهم من كتب إنجليزية حيث لا يوجد هناك قمع --
it would be like this, basically tightly centered on one.
سيكون شيئا مثل هذا، سيكون أساسا متركزا بإحكام.
What you expect is basically what you observe.
ما تتوقعونه هو ما يمكنكم ملاحظته أساسا.
This is distribution as seen in Germany --
هذا التوزيع كما يرى في ألمانيا --
very different, it's shifted to the left.
مختلف كثيرا، إنه محول قليلا لليسار.
People talked about it twice less as it should have been.
تحدث عنه الناس مرتين أقل مما يجب أن يكون.
But much more importantly, the distribution is much wider.
لكن المهم جدا، التوزيع أقل وسعا.
There are many people who end up on the far left on this distribution
هناك الكثير من الناس ينتهون في أقصى يسار التوزيع
who are talked about 10 times fewer than they should have been.
تم الحديث عنهم حوالي 10 مرات أقل مما يجب أن يكون.
But then also many people on the far right
لكن كذلك الكثير من الناس على أقصى اليسار
who seem to benefit from propaganda.
يبدو أنهم استفادوا من البروباغندا.
This picture is the hallmark of censorship in the book record.
هذه الصورة هي السمة المميزة للرقابة في سجل الكتب.
ELA: So culturomics
إ. ل. أ: الكلتروميكس
is what we call this method.
هي ما نسمي هذه الطريقة.
It's kind of like genomics.
إنها نوع ما مثل الجينوميات.
Except genomics is a lens on biology
باستثناء أن الجينوما هي عدسات على البيولوجيا
through the window of the sequence of bases in the human genome.
من خلال نافذة تسلسل القواعد في الجينوم البشري.
Culturomics is similar.
الكلتروميكس أمر مشابه.
It's the application of massive-scale data collection analysis
إنه تطبيق تحليل لمجموعة البيانات الهائلة الحجم
to the study of human culture.
لدراسة الثقافة البشرية.
Here, instead of through the lens of a genome,
هنا، على سبيل المثال من خلال عدسات الجينوم،
through the lens of digitized pieces of the historical record.
من خلال عدسات السجل التاريخي المرقمن.
The great thing about culturomics
الأمر العظيم بخصوص الكلتروميكس
is that everyone can do it.
هو أن الجميع يمكنه القيام بذلك.
Why can everyone do it?
لماذا يمكن للجميع القيام بذلك؟
Everyone can do it because three guys,
الجميع يمكنه القيام بذلك لأن ثلاثة أشخاص،
Jon Orwant, Matt Gray and Will Brockman over at Google,
جون أوروانت ومات غراي وويل بروكمان في غوغل،
saw the prototype of the Ngram Viewer,
رأوا النموذج الأولي لعارض ن-غرام،
and they said, "This is so fun.
فقالوا، "هذا في غاية المتعة.
We have to make this available for people."
علينا جعل هذا متوفرا للناس."
So in two weeks flat -- the two weeks before our paper came out --
وبالتالي في أسبوعين بالتمام -- الأسبوعان قبل صدور ورقتنا البحثية --
they coded up a version of the Ngram Viewer for the general public.
قاموا ببرمجة نسخة من عارض ن-غرام من أجل الاستخدام العام.
And so you too can type in any word or phrase that you're interested in
وبالتالي يمكنكم كذلك أن تكتبوا أي كلمة أو جملة تهتمون بها
and see its n-gram immediately --
ورؤية الـ ن-غرام مباشرة --
also browse examples of all the various books
كذلك تصفح أمثلة من مختلف الكتب
in which your n-gram appears.
حيث تظهر ن-غرام.
JM: Now this was used over a million times on the first day,
ج. م: الآن تم استخدام هذا أكثر من مليون مرة في اليوم الأول،
and this is really the best of all the queries.
وهذه بالفعل أفضل كل تلك الاستعلامات.
So people want to be their best, put their best foot forward.
وبالتالي أراد الناس وضع قدمهم الأفضل إلى الأمام.
But it turns out in the 18th century, people didn't really care about that at all.
لكن اتضح أنه في القرن الـ 18، لم يهتم الناس بذلك على الإطلاق.
They didn't want to be their best, they wanted to be their beft.
لم يريدوا أن يكونوا الأفضل، أرادوا أن يكونوا الأفدل.
So what happened is, of course, this is just a mistake.
وبالتالي ما حصل هو، بالطبع، هذا كان مجرد خطأ.
It's not that strove for mediocrity,
ليس ذلك السعي نحو التوسط،
it's just that the S used to be written differently, kind of like an F.
إنه فقط حقيقة كون الحرف ض كان يكتب بشكل مختلف، نوعا ما مثل د.
Now of course, Google didn't pick this up at the time,
الآن بالطبع، غوغل لم يلاحظ ذلك آنذاك،
so we reported this in the science article that we wrote.
وبالتالي أبلغنا عن ذلك في المقال العلمي الذي كتبناه.
But it turns out this is just a reminder
لكن اتضح أن ذلك هو فقط تذكير
that, although this is a lot of fun,
أنه، على الرغم من أنه ممتع جدا،
when you interpret these graphs, you have to be very careful,
حين تفسر تلك الرسوم البيانية، عليك أن تكون حذرا للغاية،
and you have to adopt the base standards in the sciences.
وعليك أن تعتمد المعايير الأساسية للعلوم.
ELA: People have been using this for all kinds of fun purposes.
إ. ل. أ: الناس كانوا يستخدمون جميع أنواع أغراض المتعة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Actually, we're not going to have to talk,
في الواقع، ليس علينا الكلام،
we're just going to show you all the slides and remain silent.
سنقوم فقط بعرض بقية الشرائح والبقاء صامتين.
This person was interested in the history of frustration.
هذا الشخص كان مهتما بتاريخ الإحباط.
There's various types of frustration.
هنا هذه الأنواع المختلفة من الإحباط.
If you stub your toe, that's a one A "argh."
إن صدمت اصبع قدمك، تلك آ "أرغ."
If the planet Earth is annihilated by the Vogons
إن كان كوكب الأرض أبيد من طرف الفوغونات
to make room for an interstellar bypass,
لإفساح المكان لممر بين-نجمي،
that's an eight A "aaaaaaaargh."
تلك 8 آهات "آآآآآآآآرغ."
This person studies all the "arghs,"
هذا الشخص درس كل هذه ال"آرغ".
from one through eight A's.
من واحد إلى ثمانية آهات.
And it turns out
وقد اتضح
that the less-frequent "arghs"
أن أقل الآهات استخداما
are, of course, the ones that correspond to things that are more frustrating --
هي بالطبع تلك التي ترتبط بالأشياء الأكثر احباطا
except, oddly, in the early 80s.
باستثناء، وبشكل غريب، في بداية الثمانينيات.
We think that might have something to do with Reagan.
نعتقد أن لذلك علاقة بريغان.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
JM: There are many usages of this data,
ج. م: هناك الكثير من الاستخدامات لهذه البيانات،
but the bottom line is that the historical record is being digitized.
لكن الخلاصة أن السجلات التاريخية تتم رقمنتها.
Google has started to digitize 15 million books.
غوغل قد بدأ يرقمن 15 مليون كتاب.
That's 12 percent of all the books that have ever been published.
ذلك 12 في المئة من كل الكتب التي نشرت من قبل.
It's a sizable chunk of human culture.
إنه قسم لا بأس به من الثقافة البشرية.
There's much more in culture: there's manuscripts, there newspapers,
هناك ما هو أكثر بكثير في الثقافة: هناك المخطوطات، الجرائد،
there's things that are not text, like art and paintings.
هناك الأشياء التي ليست كتابة، مثل الفن والرسومات.
These all happen to be on our computers,
كل هذا يصادف تواجده في حواسيبنا،
on computers across the world.
في حواسيب في جميع أنحاء العالم.
And when that happens, that will transform the way we have
وحين يحدث ذلك، سيغير ذلك الطريقة التي
to understand our past, our present and human culture.
نفهم بها ماضينا، وحاضرنا والثقافة البشرية.
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)